<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Hunter Stanke</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agent Based Models for Deer Dispersal Simulation</title>
      <link>/project/dispersalabm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dispersalabm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditional methods to assess landscape connectivity often fail to address functional connectivity, that is they fail to consider the behavioral patterns and movement ecology of the species of interest. In contrast, agent based models (ABMs) easily accomodate complex behaviors, social interactions, and stochasticity in animal-environment interactions. Here we build a spatially explicity ABM to model deer disperal and assess functional connectivety between two disparate zones of Chronic Wasting Disease detection in Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting the dots: landscape connectivity between locations of chronic wasting disease detection</title>
      <link>/project/lcp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/lcp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The composition and configuration of local landscapes influences animal behavior and may lead to directionally-biased movement patterns for free-ranging wild animals. Such landscape mediated animal movements may influence the directionality of emergent disease spread. Chronic wasting disease (CWD) was first discovered in free-ranging white-tailed deer of Michigan in 2015, and at the time of our analyses had been detected in nine animals from seven unique locations. Understanding the spread of CWD within this context has been a goal of state wildlife managers. We evaluated an assumed association between CWD positive animals to model potential disease spread direction using least cost path analysis and the nine detected animals. We evaluated the connectivity of habitat between CWD detection locations and assessed the potential for landscape-induced directionality of animal movement within a use-available framework. Results of this analysis showed significantly higher landscape connectivity of travel paths in an easterly direction relative to the westerly direction. Further, landscape connectivity in the easterly direction was significantly greater than expected assuming equal connectivity in all directions, while the degree of connectivity in the westerly direction was significantly lower than expected. As the distribution of CWD is associated with deer movement patterns, CWD is likely to have spread in an easterly direction across our study area, opposite the direction of detection. We provide a landscape-modeling framework for evaluating potential directional biases in ecological processes such as animal movement or disease spread.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disease Modeling with Stochastic Networks</title>
      <link>/project/networkdisease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/networkdisease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Inter-individual contact is a key element affecting the transmission of infectious disease, and variation in contact structure can affect the probability, magnitude, and persistence of disease outbreaks. Chronic Wasting Disease (CWD) is a fatal, neurodegenerative disease affecting white-tailed deer in Michigan. Previous efforts to model the spread of CWD assume that all individuals behave the same and interact one another at a constant rate, thereby assuming a homogenous contact structure. As white-tailed deer display heterogenous social structure at the population level, we expect the assumption of homogenous contact structure inherent to many disease models may result in biased representations of disease dynamics. To advance understanding of how heterogeneity in contact structure may influence the dynamics of CWD in Michigan, we will: (1) characterize the spatial, temporal, and demographic factors affecting inter-individual contact rates and individual connectedness in white-tailed deer populations; and (2) develop network-based disease models to simulate disease-host systems and assess the influence of heterogenous contact structure on disease dynamics. We will obtain GPS data from a white-tailed deer movement study in the region of Michigan where CWD is known to occur, and infer inter-individual contacts as an overlap in space (&amp;lt; 10m) and time (within 30 minutes). We will employ Bayesian linear mixed-effects models to assess how various demographic, spatial, and temporal factors affect inter-individual contact rates and social network connectivity. We will then simulate white-tailed deer social networks with similar structures to those observed, and employ spatiotemporal network-based disease models to assess the influence of host social structure on the emergence and spread of CWD. Understanding how social connectivity varies across host demographics will allow managers to focus resources towards removal of individuals at high-risk of spreading disease, and our disease modeling will help define risks and uncertainty associated with management interventions that impact host contact structures.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rFIA: Unlocking the FIA Database in R</title>
      <link>/project/rfia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/rfia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
